Guide to the Carlingford Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Carlingford papers
1651-1764
1657-1667
OSB MSS 5
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(5 boxes)
The Carlingford papers contain correspondence and diplomatic and other papers, mostly relating to Theobald Taaffe, 1st Earl of Carlingford. 24 letters signed in cipher from Charles II to Carlingford document the King's personal and political activities in the last years of his exile; other correspondence and papers concern Carlingford's diplomatic mission during the second Anglo-Dutch War, including letters by Henry Bennet, Earl of Arlington, Sir William Swan, and Sir William Temple. Other family papers include a letter concerning Carlingford's death and letters by Francis Taaffe, 3rd Earl of Carlingford, describing his military service with the Duke of Lorraine's regiment during the 1670s and 1680s.
Carlingford, Theobald Taaffe, Earl of, -1677
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase, 1969.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
THE CARLINGFORDS
Theobald Taaffe (d. 1677), a Catholic Irish loyalist, was the son of John, lst Viscount Taaffe by his wife, Anne, daughter of Sir Theobald Dillon, first raised to the peerage in 1642. During the English civil war, he joined the Catholic Confederation and participated in negotiations between Irish Confed- erates and the party led by James Butler, Earl of Ormond. He served as commander of the Irish forces in Munster (1647) and Master of the Ordinance (1649). In 1650, he was sent to the Continent to negotiate with Charles IV, Duke of Lorraine, for assistance to the king's followers in Ireland.
During the 1650's, Taaffe remained on the Continent, serving the exiled Charles II as informal counselor and boon companion, described by Charles II as "one of the best Dancers in the Country, and is the chief man at all the Balls" (Crist, p. 10).
Taaffe's personality, and his Catholicism, made him a useful representative of the king in both personal and diplomatic affairs. He served as a liaison between Charles II and several of his mistresses, in particular, Lucy Walter. He also met with various Catholic leaders such as Don Alonzo de Cardenas, the Duke of Lorraine, the count of Neuburg and the Papal Nuncio, among others.
After the Restoration, Charles II rewarded Taaffe for his years of loyal service, granting him an annuity of eight hundred pounds and restoring him to his estates in Ireland. On 26 June 1661, Taaffe was created 1st Earl of Carlingford in the Irish peerage.
Carlingford's final diplomatic mission took place during the second Anglo Dutch War (1665-67). In 1665, he was sent as Envoy-Extraordinary from Charles II to Leopold I, Emperor of Germany, and the prince-bishop of Munster in order to gain support for the English cause against the Dutch. He replaced Sir William Temple, who had no taste for the kind of sociability expected in German courts. Carlingford, on the other hand, was known as "a fattey man and a good Drinker, which is a condition very necessary in banquetts, where he is every day" (Lachs, p. 64). His mission, however, was not a success. The Venetian ambassador complained that Carlingford "in no way corresponded to the greatness of the occasion," being "destitute of the knowledge and ability required for such transactions" (Crist, p. 12). After he returned to England, Carlingford retired from public life. He died on 31 December 1677.
Carlingford married, first, Mary, daughter of Sir Nicholas White of Leixlip, county Kildare; and, secondly, Anne, daughter of Sir William Pershall. By his first wife he had three sons and a daughter: Nicholas, 2nd Earl, who served in the Spanish army and fell at the Boyne in 1691; Francis, 3rd Earl, page to emperors Ferdinand III and Leopold I and, later, an Austrian field-marshal; and John (d. 1689).
For additional biographical information see: Timothy Crist, ed., Charles II to Lord Taaffe: Letters in Exile (Rampant Lions Press: Cambridge, 1974) and Phyllis S. Lachs, The Diplomatic Corps under Charles II and James II (Rutgers University Press: New Brunswick, New Jersey, 1965)
Scope and Contents
The Carlingford Papers consist of correspondence and diplomatic and other papers of the Earls of Carlingford and other members of the Carlingford family. They document, chiefly, Charles II's activities during his years in exile and the mission of Theobald Taaffe, 1st Earl of Carlingford, as Envoy to Emperor Leopold I and the Prince-Bishop of Munster. Various papers of his sons, Nicholas and Francis, also are included in the collection. The Carlingford Papers span the years 1651-1764 but the bulk of the material covers the periods 1657-59 and 1665-67.
Series I, Charles II Letters to Theobald Taaffe, 2nd Viscount Taaffe, contains letters written by the exiled king to Taaffe, his friend and companion, during the period 1655-60. The letters, unsigned but concluded with a cipher, provide a rare insight into Charles' personality.
Series II, Theobald Taaffe Papers, (2nd Viscount Taaffe and 1st Earl of Carlingford) contains letters and diplomatic papers relating to Carlingford's embassy, his correspondence with the Prince-Bishop of Munster and with other English envoys such as Henry Coventry in Stockholm, Sir William Temple in Brussels, Sir William Swan in Hamburg, Lord Sandwich in Madrid and with Lord Arlington, Secretary of State. Other items concern German princes, including Ernst Augustus, Elector of Hanover, and Georg Wilhelm, Duke of Brunswick-Luneburg.
Series III, Later Carlingford Papers, contains a letter to Nicholas Taaffe, 3rd Viscount Taaffe and 2nd Earl, from several Irish noblemen concerning his father's death, letters from Francis Taaffe, 3rd Earl of Carlingford, to his father and others describing the political and military situation in Europe, c. 1670-84, and a letter from the King of Portugal to the Emperor of Germany concerning Nicholas, 6th Viscount Taaffe.
Series IV, Curatorial Files, contains supplementary material from the curator's files related to the Carlingford Papers which may be of interest to researchers. These include Timothy Crist's published transcriptions of the letters from Charles II to the Earl of Carlingford, catalogue descriptions of other letters of Charles II, articles concerning the provenance of the Charles II letters to Carlingford by Timothy Crist and Stephen Parks, and other secondary source material related to the Restoration period.
Anglo-Dutch War, 1664-1667; Diplomatic and consular service, British; Budapest (Hungary) -- History -- Siege, 1684; Great Britain -- Court and courtiers; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- 1660-1714; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- Holy Roman Empire; Great Britain -- History -- Charles II, 1660-1685; Great Britain -- History -- Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660; Diplomats -- Great Britain; Bernhard, Prince-Bishop of M端nster, 1606-1678; Charles, King of England, II, 1630-1685; Leopold, Holy Roman Emperor, I, 1640-1705; Sophia, Electress, consort of Ernest Augustus, Elector of Hanover, 1630-1714; Arlington, Henry Bennet, Earl of, 1618-1685; Carlingford, Francis Taaffe, Earl of, 1639-1704; Carlingford, Theobald Taaffe, Earl of, -1677; Clarendon, Henry Hyde, Earl of, 1609-1674; Coventry, Henry, 1619-1686; Elisabeth, Countess Palatine, 1618-1680; Sandwich, Edward Montagu, Earl of, 1625-1672; Swan, William, Sir, d. 1678; Temple, William, 1628-1699; Williamson, Joseph, Sir, 1633-1701
- Charles II Letters to 2nd Viscount Taaffe, 1655-60, n.d.; Series I; 0.25; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  The text of these letters is available in a published edition: Charles II to Lord Taaffe: Letters in Exile, ed. Timothy Crist (Cambridge: Rampant Lions Press, 1974.) The dating of letters in the Crist edition has been incorporated into this listing. Letters are arranged chronologically. The abbreviation n.s. indicates dates in the 'new style' format.
  - CHARLES II, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1630-85
    - ALS, Cologne., [1655 May] 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      1 p.; 21 x 31 cm.
    - ALS, Brussels., [1656] Dec 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      1 p.; 20 x 31 cm.
    - ALS, Bruges., [1656] Dec 26 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - ALS, Bruges., [1657 Jan 2] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - ALS, Bruges., 1657 Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 1 p.; 21 x 31 cm., [n.s.]
    - ALS, [Antwerp or Bruges]., [1657] Feb 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - 2 p.; 21 x 31 cm., [n.s.]
    - ALS, Bruges., [1657 Feb 13] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 1 p.; 22 x 31 cm., [n.s.]
    - ALS, Bruges., [1657] March 21 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - 1 p.; 23 x 34 cm., [n.s.]
    - ALS, [Bruges]., [Spring 1657] (Box 1, Folder 9)
      1 p.; 21 x 15 cm.
    - ALS, [Bruges?]., 1657 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ALS, Dunkirk., [1657] Nov 5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      1 p.; 23 x 34 cm.
    - ALS, Dunkirk., [1657] Nov 18 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      1 p.; 20 x 30 cm.
    - ALS, [Bruges]., [1657] Dec 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ALS, [n.p.]., [1657 Dec] (Box 1, Folder 14)
      1 p.; 22 x 18 cm.
    - ALS, [n.p.]., [1658 Feb or (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - 1 p.; 19 x 15 cm., or March, n.s.]
    - ALS, [Brussels]., [1658] Mar 19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - 1 p.; 21 x 31 cm., [n.s.]
    - ALS, Brussels., [1658] Jun 23 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      2 p.; 21 x 31 cm.
    - ALS, Brussels., [1658] Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      1 p.; 21 x 30 cm.
    - ALS, [n.p.]., [1659] Feb 19 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - 2 p.; 22 x 31 cm., [n.s.]
    - ALS, [n.p.]., [1659] Mar 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - 2 p.; 22 x 15 cm., [n.s.]
    - ALS, Fuenterrabia., [1659] Oct 31 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      1 p.; 23 x 24 cm.
    - ALS, [Breda]., [1660] Apr 6 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - ALS, [n.p.]., [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - ALS, [n.p.]., [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Theobald Taaffe, 1st Earl of Carlingford, Papers, 1651-77, n.d.; Series II; 0.75; (2 boxes)
  Organized into Correspondence (Incoming, Outgoing and Third-Party arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent) and Papers.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Incoming
      - Unidentified senders
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, London, 1663 July 11 (Box 2, Folder 25)
          Report on the effort by George Digby, 2nd Earl of Bristol, to impeach Edward Hyde, 1st Earl of Clarendon.
        - Letter (copy) to the Earl of Carlingford, Madrid, 1666 Sep 12 (Box 2, Folder 26)
          Concerning the attempt to negotiate a treaty with Spain.
        - AL to the Earl of Carlingford, [n.y.] Feb 21 (Box 2, Folder 27)
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Arlington, Henry Bennet, 1st Earl of, 1618-1685
        - 7 LS to the Earl of Carlingford, Salisbury and Oxford, 1665 Sept 23-Dec 21 (Box 2, Folder 29)
          - Letters to Carlingford, envoy from Charles II to Bernhard, prince- bishop of M端nster, and Leopold I, Emperor of Germany, with instructions and reactions concerning efforts to gain support for the English cause against the Dutch.
        - 9 LS to the Earl of Carlingford, Oxford and Whitehall, 1665/6 Jan 11-1666 Apr 27 (Box 2, Folder 30)
        - 8 LS to the Earl of Carlingford, Whitehall, 1666 Jun 11-Aug 24 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Bernhard, Prince-Bishop of M端nster, 1606-1678
        - 9 LS and 1 copy to the Earl of Carlingford, various places, 1665 Oct 14-1666 May 14 (Box 2, Folder 32)
          - Concerning activities in Germany and the Prince-Bishop of M端nster's involvement during the second Anglo- Dutch War.
        - Letter (translated copy) to the Earl of Carlingford, [1666 Dec.] (Box 2, Folder 33)
          Acknowledgment of the credentials of the Earl of Carlingford.
      - Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685
        - Instruction for the Earl of Carlingford as Extraordinary Envoy to Leopold I, Emperor of Germany, Salisbury, 1665 Aug 22 (Box 2, Folder 34)
          Signed and initialled by Charles II. Countersigned by Lord Arlington.
          Carlingford is instructed to have conferences with the Marquis Castel Rodrigo; William Temple; Bernhard, Prince-Bishop of M端nster; and Emperor Leopold I.
          Accompanied by a copy of further instructions, in French, dated 1666 Jun 22 at Whitehall, by letters of introduction signed by Charles II for Carlingford to Carolus Caspar, Johann Friedrich and Georg Wilhelm.
          Also accompanied by copies of other letters of introduction and by a copy of a letter intended for Emperor Leopold.
          11 items total.
      - Clanricarde, William Bourke, 7th Earl of, d. 1687
        - LS to the Earl of Carlingford, Loghreagh, 1676 Aug 27 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Clarendon, Edward Hyde, 1st Earl of, 1609-1674
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Oxford, [1665] Dec 17 (Box 2, Folder 36)
          Concerns the Prince-Bishop of M端nster's promise to aid the English in the second Anglo-Dutch War.
        - 2 letters (copies) to Father Donellan, Brussels, [1658] Apr 13, 1658 Oct 19 (Box 2, Folder 37)
          - Request to help maintain the goodwill of the German court toward Charles II.
      - Coventry, Henry, 1619-1686
        - 5 ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Stockholm, 1665/66 Feb 17-1666 Apr 4 (Box 2, Folder 38)
          - Reports from Stockholm where Coventry was envoy and messages concerning efforts to obtain repayment of Carlingford's debts incurred while in Germany.
        - 11 ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Whitehall and Windsor, 1674-1677/8 Jan 12 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Curtius, Sir William, d.1690
        - 4 ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Frankfurt, 1665 Nov 21-1666 May 15/25 (Box 2, Folder 40)
          - Letters concerning the aid of Curtius to Carlingford's diplomatic efforts with the Prince-Bishop of M端nster. Also contains an extract of a letter from Heidleberg to Curtius.
      - Donellan, Nicholas
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, 1666 Nov 11 (Box 2, Folder 41)
          Father Donnellan appears to have gathered information at the German Court for the English. This letter reports on circumstances occurring after Carlingford's departure.
      - Donnily, B. G.
        - ALS to Theobold Taaffe, 2nd Viscount Taaffe, 1660/1 Jan 14 (Box 2, Folder 42)
          Request that Taaffe present to Charles II Donnily's case for reim- bursement of debts.
      - Egmont, Comte de
        - LS to the Earl of Carlingford, Brussels, 1666 Sep 4 (Box 2, Folder 43)
          Enclosed declaration of claim to family lands in Holland.
      - Elisabeth, Countess Palatine, Abbess of Herford, 1618-1680
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Herford, 1666 Aug 23 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - Ernst August, Elector of Hanover, 1629-1698
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Celle, [1665?] Nov 3 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - Friedrich of Hesse-Darmstadt, Prince- Bishop of Breslau, Cardinal, 1615-1682
        - LS to the Earl of Carlingford, Rome, 1666 Sept 2 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - Georg Wilhelm, Duke of Brunswick- L端neborg, 1624-1705
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Celle, 1665 Nov 7 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - Jollyvet, E
        - 2 ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Hamburg, 1666 Sep 22-1666 Sep 29 (Box 2, Folder 48)
          - Reports on affairs in the vicinity of the town of Bremen. Jollyvet was apparently a secretary to Sir William Swan.
      - Lamberg, Comte de
        - 2 ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Luxemburg; one in French, one in Latin, 1666 May-n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49)
          Concerning Carlingford's diplomatic mission in Germany.
      - Leslie, Walter, Count Leslie, 1606-1667 (Box 2, Folder 49a)
        - 4 ALS and 2 LS to the Earl of Carlingford, Adrianople, Vienna, [Dossey], and [Brin], 1666 Jan 4 [n.s.]-1666 Jul 5
      - Lobkowitz, Furst von
        - LS to the Earl of Carlingford, 1666 Apr 14 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - Martinitz, Count R. C.
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Prague, 1666 May 25 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - Maximilian Heinrich of Bavaria, abp. and Elector of Cologne, 1621-1688
        - LS to the Earl of Carlingford, Arnsberg, 1665 Oct 4 (Box 2, Folder 52)
          Accompanied by copy in Latin of letter from Maximilian to Charles II.
      - Oliva, Giovanni Paulo, general of the Jesuits, 1600-1681
        - LS to the Earl of Carlingford, Rome, 1665 Aug 1 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - Ormonde, James Butler, 1st Duke of, 1610-1688
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Whitehall, 1668/9 Jan 26 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      - Philipp Wilhelm of Neuberg, Elector Palatine, 1615-1690
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Bensberg, 1665 Oct 1 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      - Plaidus, Father
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Lambspring, 1666 Jul 5 (Box 2, Folder 56)
          Concerning a recent naval battle.
      - St. Albans, Henry Jermyn, 1st Earl of, d.1684
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, 1666 Aug 26 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      - Sandwich, Edward Montagu, 1st Earl of, 1625-1672
        - 2 LS to the Earl of Carlingford, Madrid, 1666 Sep 23-Oct. 12 (Box 2, Folder 58)
          - A large portion of the first letter is in cipher.
      - Sophie, consort of Ernest Augustus, Elector of Hanover, 1630-1714
        - 2 LS and 1 copy to the Earl of Carlingford, Celle and Osnabruck, 1665 Nov 3-Nov 12 (Box 2, Folder 59)
          - Concerning Carlingford's diplomatic mission in Germany during the second Anglo-Dutch War.
      - Swan, Sir William, d.1678
        - 5 ALS and 2 LS to the Earl of Carlingford, Hamburg, 1665 Sep 23-1666 May 19 (Box 2, Folder 60)
          - Swan was the English envoy in Hamburg during the second Anglo- Dutch War.
      - Taaffe, James, Franciscan Friar, fl. 1666
        - ALS to [the Earl of Carlingford], Brussels, 1666 May 22 (Box 2, Folder 61)
          Regrets being unable to receive Carlingford in Paris.
        - 2 ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, St. Isidore, 1671 Aug-Dec 19 (Box 2, Folder 62)
          - Defenses against attacks on his character and reports about the Court in Rome.
      - Talbot, Sir Gilbert, 1607?-1695
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Copenhagen, 1666 Feb 13 [n.s.] (Box 2, Folder 63)
          Warning about an attempt to influ- ence Emperor Leopold I of Germany to the detriment of English interests.
      - Temple, Sir William, 1628-1699
        - 8 ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Brussels, 1665 Dec 3, 1666 Feb 27, n.s. (Box 2, Folder 64)
          Letters concerning affairs in the second Anglo-Dutch War, especially naval conflicts, with several interesting anecdotes.
        - 5 ALS and 3 LS to the Earl of Carlingford, Brussels, 1666 Mar 6-Aug 7, n.s. (Box 2, Folder 65)
        - 6 ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Brussels, 1666 Aug 14-Sept 24, n.s. (Box 2, Folder 66)
          Includes a copy of Carlingford's considerations intended for Temple.
      - Williamson, Sir Joseph, 1633-1701
        - 3 ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Oxford and Whitehall, 1665 Oct 19-1666 Jul 27 (Box 2, Folder 67)
          Reports concerning the progress in the second Anglo-Dutch War and the state of affairs in England. The third letter contains a copy of a detailed report about a naval battle near Harwich on 1666 Jul 25.
      - Winchilsea, Heneage Finch, 2nd Earl of, 1628-1689
        - ALS to the Earl of Carlingford, Belgrade, 1666 Aug 17 (Box 2, Folder 68)
          Winchilsea was ambassador at Constantinople during this time.
    - Outgoing
      - AL (draft) to Murrough O'Brien, 1st Earl of Inchiquin, 1651 Jun 9 (Box 3, Folder 69)
        Concerns the negotiations between Carlingford and Charles V, Duke of Lorraine, about support of Ireland and the difficulties which Carlingford encountered.
      - ALS (copy) to James, Duke of York, later James II, King of England, Brussels, 1651 Jun 14 (Box 3, Folder 70)
      - ALS (draft?) to [Princess Elisabeth, countess Palatine, abbess of Herford], Vienna, 1666 Jan 23 [n.s.] (Box 3, Folder 71)
        Concerns Elisabeth's plans to become a nun, and Carlingford's objections to them.
      - 5 letters (copies) to Bernhard, Prince- Bishop of M端nster, 1665 Oct 10-1666 Feb 18 [n.s.] (Box 3, Folder 72)
      - Letter (fragment of a draft) to an unnamed recipient, [c. 1665-66] (Box 3, Folder 73)
        Discusses his negotiation with various German nobles concerning their position in the second Anglo-Dutch War.
      - 2 ALS (drafts?) to [Princess Sophie, consort of Ernest Augustus, Elector of Hanover], Vienna, 1666 Jan 14 [n.s.]-1666 Aug 12 (Box 3, Folder 74)
        "...I hear the wealth of the French has great influence in Germany, but that as yet you have resisted the tem[p]tation..."
      - Collection of drafts, copies and fragments of the Earl of Carlingford's letters, 21 items, [c. 1665-67] (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Third-Party Correspondence
      - Unidentified correspondents
        - ALS to [?], the Hague, 1665 Oct 10 (Box 3, Folder 76)
          Heading reads: "Serenisme Prince Monseigneur"
      - Arlington, Henry Bennet, 1st Earl of, 1618-1685
        - ALS in French (recipient unknown), 1665 Dec. 21 (Box 3, Folder 76a)
      - Bernhard, Prince-Bishop of M端nster, 1606-1678
        - 2 letters (copies) to Charles II, Meppen, 1665 Oct 22-Oct 25 (Box 3, Folder 77)
      - Friedrich Wilhelm, Elector of Branden- burg, called the Great Elector, 1620-1688
        - Letter (copy) to Charles II, Hamburg, 1665 Nov 11 (Box 3, Folder 78)
        - Letter (copy) to Georg Wilhelm, Hamburg, 1665 Nov 12 (Box 3, Folder 79)
      - Georg Wilhelm, Duke of Brunswick- L端neborg, 1624-1705
        - Letter (copy) to Charles II, Celle, 1665 Oct 26 (Box 3, Folder 80)
          Acknowledging the Earl of Carling- ford's commission as Envoy.
      - Hedwig, Sophia, 1623-1683
        - Letter (copy) to Charles II, 1665 Nov 16 (Box 3, Folder 81)
      - Johann Friedrich, Duke of Brunswick- L端neborg, 1625-1679
        - Letter (copy) to Charles Il, Hanover, 1665 Oct 26 (Box 3, Folder 82)
      - Lamberg, Comte de
        - LS to Francisco de Maura, 3rd marques de Castel-Rodrigo, 1666 Apr 14 (Box 3, Folder 83)
      - Leopold I, Emperor of Germany, 1640-1705
        - 6 letters (copies) to Charles II, Vienna; 5 in Latin; one in English, 1666 Apr 12-Nov 7 (Box 3, Folder 84)
        - Empty folder (Box 3, Folder 85)
      - Lionne, Hughes de, 1611-1671
        - Letter (copy) to ambassador of France, 1665 Dec 25 (Box 3, Folder 86)
      - Louvois, Francois Michel le Tellier, marquis de, 1641-1691
        - Letter (deciphered copy) to the Duke of Luxembourg, Versailles, 1676 Aug 25 (Box 3, Folder 87)
      - Netherlands (United Provinces, 1581-1795) Staten General
        - Letter (copy) to Charles II, The Hague, 1665 Dec 11 (Box 3, Folder 88)
      - Terlon, Hughes de, 17th cent.
        - ALS to an unnamed recipient, Stockholm, 1665 Sep 23 (Box 3, Folder 89)
      - Williamson, Sir Joseph, 1633-1701
        - Les propositions des Ambassadeurs de France au Roi de Grande Bretagne touchant un accomodement avec les Etats: holograph, 1665 21/31 Oct (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - PAPERS
    - [Account of naval battle between England and Holland on 1666 Sep 3: Latin manuscript], [1666 Oct 29] (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Les considerations du Sr. Friquet a Monsieur le Pensionnaire de Witt pour la paix avec Monsieur l'Evesque de M端nster, [n.d.] (Box 3, Folder 92)
      Signed "Jean Dillon"
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 3, Folder 93)
      Letters and documents on various topics concerning Carlingford's mission, affairs in Ireland, and activities of the Canary Company. 9 items total. 6 in Latin, one each in Italian, French, and English.
- Later Carlingford Papers, Dates 1670-1764; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  Organized into three subseries: Nicholas Taaffe, 2nd Earl of Carlingford, Papers; Francis Taaffe, 3rd Earl of Carlingford, Papers; and Nicholas Taaffe, 6th Viscount Taaffe, Papers.
  - NICHOLAS TAAFFE (d. 1691), 2ND EARL OF CARLINGFORD, PAPERS
    - Clanricarde, William Bourke, 7th Earl of, d. 1687.
      - LS to the Earl of Carlingford, Portumna, 1677/8 Jan 8 (Box 4, Folder 94)